In this video, I will be demonstrating how to create an
accessible modal dialog using the HTML5  tag.
It uses a polyfill for browsers
that don't support it yet natively.
For details on the
polyfill and more information on how this demo was
built,
please checkout the video's accompanying
blog post on useragentman.com.
The first browser we are going to demonstrate is
Safari using VoiceOver, which is built into OSX.
Right now, keyboard focus is on the link just
before the button labelled "Log in to our website",
which will open the modal when pressed.
So, let's use the keyboard to
navigate to the button...
[VoiceOver says: Log in to our website, button, main, two items]
and now we'll hit the enter key.
[VoiceOver says: Close this dialog, web dialog, login, 1 item. In order to continue, please log into the application.]
You may have noticed that when the dialog
opened, the close button gains focus.
Also, note that the screen reader
said "close this dialog, button".
This tells the screen reader user that focus
is on a button labelled "close this dialog".
(Incidentally, this label was coded as
alt attribute for the button's  tag).
You'll also note that the screen
reader reports it is a web dialog.
That's because the button is
inside a HTML  tag.
VoiceOver would also announce this if the modal was coded as a  tag with its role attribute set to "dialog".
In fact, setting the role to dialog is what the polyfill does on all  dialog tags so screen readers can report the dialog properly to the user.
Finally, you will notice the screen reader reads
out the header, and the description in the dialog.
This happens because the  tag has its
aria-labelledby attribute set to the id of the header,
and its aria-describedby attribute
set the id of the description text.
Now, let's find out what happens when
we tab past the end of the dialog.
[VoiceOver: Username, edit text with autofill menu.]
[Password, secure edit text with...]
[Cancel, button.]
[Confirm, button.]
[Close this dialog, button.]
You'll notice that when I hit the tab key after the "Confirm" button, focus goes to the first element in the dialog.
Focus never goes to any interactive
element behind the modal.
For browsers that support the  tag, this
automatically happens because it is native browser behavior.
However, for browsers that don't, the polyfill
steps in and uses focus events to implement this.
If focus goes outside the dialog,
it loops back to the first element of the modal...
if we are tabbing forward, of course.
If we are tabbing backward, using a shift-TAB,
then focus goes the last element of the modal.
And now, let's find out what
happens when I close the modal...
[VoiceOver: Login in to our website, button, main, 2 items.]
You'll notice that focus is placed
back to the button that opened it.
Surprisingly, this is not default browser behavior, even though this is considered best practice in the WAI-ARIA documentation.
It is added by a bit of code in the
polyfill.
This code is executed for all browsers, including those with native support for the dialog tag.
Now let's look at Google Chrome using
Android's built in screen reader, Talkback.
I am using a Samsung tablet for this demonstration, but the behavior for this  device is, more or less, the same on any Android device using this software.
I'm going to start by navigating to the link
just before the button that opens the modal.
Since this device doesn't have a keyboard, Talkback users must swipe left and right to navigate back and forth within the document.
[(Talkback says short beginnings of dialog while user swipes through text)]
[Talkback: Creating Accessible HTML5 Modal Dialogs for Desktop and Modal, link.]
[Log in to our website, button, out of list.]
You'll also note that it looks like focus is not just going to the interactive elements on the page (like the tab key does on a keyboard enabled device).
Instead, Talkback's so-called "accessibility focus"
goes to all the items on the page that can be read.
This is default behavior for Talkback, and iOS's
VoiceOver screen reader has similar behavior.
This can be changed, but I will
leave that for a future video.
Now let's double tap to
activate this button.
[Talkback: Close this dialog, button. Double-tap to activate.]
Again, you will notice that
focus goes to the close button.
However, unlike VoiceOver, Talkback didn't
read the dialog's heading or the description.
It also doesn't mention that you
are now inside a web dialog.
This is because different screen readers don't
support all the ARIA-attributes equally.
This is the reason why I chose "close this dialog"
as the alt attribute for the close button image.
It tells the user that they are inside a dialog, even if a
particular screen reader doesn't support the dialog role.
This is a good example that, just like in all aspects of web development, you should use progressive-enhancement to make your code bullet-proof.
Now, let's try to swipe backwards past the
close button at the beginning of the dialog.
[Talkback says: Creating An Accessible Dialog Using the HTML5 Dialog Tag, web view.]
You'll notice that focus doesn't go behind the modal,
just like when I was using a desktop screen reader.
However, this is not because of the
focus events I described earlier.
The problem with most (if not all) mobile screen readers is that they don't fire focus and blur events back to the browser when swiping over the document.
In order to code this behavior on mobile, developers must set aria-hidden= "true" to all elements outside of the modal dialog.
This may seem a little scary if you have a lot
of interactive elements outside the dialog,
I mean, who wants to set aria-hidden
attributes on all of those DOM nodes?
However, this is an efficient algorithm to do this, and
it's in the blog post that accompanies this video.
If you are playing this video on the YouTube website,
the link to the post is the description below it.
Hope this demonstration was helpful! Please
feel free to comment on the my YouTube page,
or my blog, useragentman.com. I'd
love to hear your feedback. Thank you.