good afternoon and bonjour to tattoos we
will start with the latest numbers on
covert 19 in Canada there are now
seventy nine thousand four hundred
ninety one cases including five thousand
nine hundred and fifty five deaths and
forty thousand three hundred forty two
or fifty one percent have now recovered
labs across Canada have tested over 1
million three hundred and seventy two
thousand people for testing and to date
with about five percent of these testing
positive overall and we're now testing
an average of twenty eight thousand or
so people a day these numbers change
quickly and are updated regularly on
Canada CA / coronavirus as Canada's
covert 19 epidemic continues to slow and
province and territories proceed with
careful reopening plans we are thinking
more and more about how to proceed
through the spring and summer months and
what to plan for in the fall vigilance
and patience would be our biggest
virtues during this time until effective
therapies or vaccine is widely available
our aim must be to carefully balance the
direct risks associated the cove in 19m
ik activity with the unintended Health
social inking and economic consequences
that means we opening to lessen negative
consequences while maintaining core
Public Health practices to keep covert
19 activity to a low level for the
spring and summer months strict
adherence to the public health basics
our physical distancing hand-washing and
cough etiquette must continue as the
bare minimum in addition we're covert 19
activity is occurring use of non-medical
masks or face coverings is recommended
as an added layer of protection when
physical distancing is difficult to
maintain and staying home when sick is a
must always and everywhere we will be
posting updated federal provincial
territorial special Advisory Committee
on covert nineteen's recommendation on
the non-medical mass today if we can all
maintain these measures to the best of
our ability we stand the best chance
keeping covert 19 activity down through
the spring and summer this will give us
morally time to work on full range of
preparedness activities in readiness for
whatever may come this fall and winter
as well suppressing disease activities
throughout the summer will continue to
buy time for research and innovation our
medical therapies and vaccine
development I know this may not be the
grand reopening we might have light but
we won't get through this on hope alone
for the weeks and months ahead we'll
need to continue to prop each other up
with creativity kindness and patience
when it comes to summer reopening
keeping our two metres is a must
outside spaces are better than insert
small bubbles of core contacts are
better than big and good hand-washing is
the right accessory for all venues and
occasions Thank You Massie mojo come
debited Sheba come on sit back lay down
your shifter concern or lack of it is
new for Canada via met no sauce on D
sniff mill cats on cat Carino's yeah
don't thank me
nips on second say they say a cat hot
meal twice on calendar Vijay please no
Sookie correspond Stan County on perks
on dks2 Jalil Ibaka to ugly she'll do
Canada on analyse elitist paliku VD
sniffed duplicity Amelia twice--once was
on dues mill back son
you're here on set box on detest
effectuates the song reveal a positive
on Wayan do tests on actual ma / wrong
van with mill tax on tax yo see Chiffre
Evol you rapid ma is a song regularly
Akmal mrs. jock solicit canada points
era back oblique lute Godinho coroner
vegas a mazurka lepida media covetous
new for canada continued our gallant ear
Akali province le territoire
metal nerve rally plum the director of
briefly she do new passion Devon
T'Challa fasten the proceed a or pronto
ele t a solid plan pollutant the
vigilance l'apicio's sir only no
playground virtue pond instead period
juice
certain vaccine will turn on Africa's
soil asthma
excessive not the objective dois etre
dossier in equilibria tilaka entre Degas
direct associate al activity epidemic
della covetousness La Casa cost senator
socio-economic in a town do solar
signifi replace this activity per
continually consequence negative
two-tone continual deprecated predict
the Santi public the bass from it near
activity relative at a covetous nerve
are in Feb la nieve oh-oh pronto a islet
a default will continue e go straight
minimum the swivel a lateral oppressive
the Bastille Asante public a savoir the
distance the ASEAN visit the lavash name
a in the irregular design Crespi Hardt
work on otra on card activity relative
Alec Ava's desist covetousness the
Portland mask no medical wooden Cobra
visage a Rock'em and a commuter the
protection supplement a mostly deficit
the met near the distal Co Co physical
over publish the recommendation the
committee consultative special of
Jacques three est La Mesa
lost colony Malad it s RCL on to tau P
and Paco norsu truth sinew proven truth
maniac similar Emiliano capacity new
Maximus only chance the limit a lack
tivity relative at a covetous Neve
open-toe a islet a new genre insipid
Tompa travailler I invest a vaunted
activity the preparation on provision
the zookeeper a Aviv a settled on a
sativa the + su criminal activity della
melody pond a lady new parameter the
continued a the Gagne prefer progress a
latter chefs elena vasya
solid cut non-medical enemies or point
than vaccine Newsome Cassio cousin
epilogue rendre please this activity
canoes Oreo suet a Mela spa
sir new new parametric apply the sake of
the said freeze Oh God
the same any de moi venir the Devron
continue a the new sudeerneer of a clear
TBT be envious apostles Oh sir key
concern lever priest his activity
Estevan the main change in distance the
geometrical it it it is on CL before
Musa - v al exterior and interior the
prefer Gabaldon katha near the pit
exactly socio to Tokido grow in bolivars
MA it shows FL on to tau Maxie
Thank You doctors we will now open the
telephone line and the florida questions
have proposed a vocational you new lungs
of shell movin on the who at limited and
guess no in kissing on this TV for those
who wish to ask question in the room
please make your way over to the freely
standing mic we will start on the phone
as usual over to you operator Murphy
thank you the next question is from
Alina Dib
please go ahead with bulimia we dr.
Newsome like the room expletives
economies are not up to budget met now
welcome our day the problem ask no
medical recovery - Eska Desna a Capuchin
a compound per tutta la nostra humility
mr. Paulo question Oh anything a Babu
could the difference but the difference
the towards describe doctor time one day
Jocasta on continue no discussion of
Ignacio Moloch de Provence it territoire
a mecca of civilian deliciosa on DK
set in misery supplement le4 - jacques a
crayon a deep usually literally the
master the caliber media the media
medical parole a daily travels
constantly solitary may parallelogram
public sia on attorney second star so
you see papa said that the guardian a
distillation of physically geometrical
said in in in oatmeal supplement a
missile CSS AOC the paid upon down the
circumstance pascal lately epidemiology
Suvari a generational load say circa see
own italy slur transparent coma
lore'l certain situational comedy for
all copper grab that owner target while
you can
Maxie okay maybe so maybe my next one
would be for you dr. Tam so so what
exactly has changed for you now to say
we recommend because you were saying
that the mask does not protect the
person that was wearing it I am assuming
that this is still the case so what has
changed for you now to go the extra step
and not just say this is a good idea
this can be done now it is we recommend
that you do this mm-hmm yep so that's
it's a specific recommendation if you
like are supposed to be I think the
previous language was more permissive so
I think just to rewind a little bit the
chief medical officers position from the
start was that of course these masts
protect others so if you're wearing it
you're protecting other people against
your droplets so at the start it was put
obviously someone who is sick who is
coughing or sneezing if they're going to
go out or have to go to a medical
appointment for example they need to
cover the calf and and with facial
covering or mass that is for the sick
person so it's when we got more evidence
about asymptomatic and pre-symptomatic
individuals and that although we don't
fully understand their role in
transmission it is an added layer of
protection even for people who don't
have symptoms to wear masks to prevent
transmission to others and even though
the evidence space hasn't changed too
much and particularly as people have
generally been staying at home
particularly and now that we are sort of
reopening or restarting a lot of the
activities the chief McArthur's felt
that they can recommend this for people
who cannot maintain that 2 meter
distance and more specifically if of
course if there's virus in your
there's been a community transmission in
your jurisdiction and I start a new said
you know jurisdictions felt that they
need to do that risk assessment because
there's some provinces and territories
that haven't had community transmission
and others have clearly have and
continues to have community transmission
activities so they will do the
individual risk assessments in terms of
the various specific recommendations
locally but I think you know from our
perspective it is an added layer of
protection it is for you to protect
others so if two people are in Mass I'm
protecting you and you're protecting me
and so I think as more people do go out
in the community you can imagine
there'll be more people on public
transport or maybe more people some of
the retail stores are beginning to open
for example and if you can't predict
whether you can maintain that to me the
distance then is recommended that you
wear the non-medical masks or facial
covering merci docteur next next
question operator thank you the next
question is from Mike Blanche field from
The Canadian Press please go ahead yeah
hi I guess this is a question for dr.
Tam we've seen radically different
approaches in the provinces to largest
provinces Ontario Quebec on reopening
you know especially when it comes to
schooling especially and we heard what
Dark Lord said yesterday how do you
explain the differences an approach to
reopening easing of restrictions and
these two highly afflicted Canada to
largest provinces so at the federal
level and working with the provinces
essentially the chief medical officers
we we have provided guidance and
criteria but obviously the provinces
want to retain their own ability to
adjust their approaches as I think even
in the global context I don't know that
there's
absolute white halfway down this curve
as I've said people have to do whatever
they do cautiously and slowly using the
best information they have in their own
particular contexts and that if they
were you know reopening or loosening
certain measures they need to have the
necessary systems to detect whether that
has led to and the increase in cases or
clusters so I think whatever pathway
down this curve there is no
one-size-fits-all and there is a certain
element of uncertainty but if you do it
more cautiously and monitor it and
adjust as needed that is the key
principle thank you follow-up all right
well how do you square the differences
anyway I mean there are two very similar
provinces similar sets of circumstances
does it surprise you from a scientific
point of view that two extremely
different conclusions can be reached
under these circumstances well I think
as the local jurisdictions one aspect
which are not sure is particularly
evident is that I think Public Health is
also trying to take a holistic approach
not just balancing these are the
effective public health measures but
also looking at the negative
consequences as well you need to have
some balance you need to bring back
certain activities and certain measures
getting people outside for instance the
outside is less risk because we know
transmission generally occurs and
particularly transmission to large
numbers people occurs indoors and so I
think all of those has to be taken to
account but in some areas there may be a
good reason why certain things are being
opened and in order to support the
community in their local context as well
and it's a balance between the need to
reduce the spread of disease compared to
all the other
from a health social and economic
perspective it's afternoon I guess we
would add that even and with any
province you can see their differences
because obviously the provincial
authorities know more what's happening
on the ground dr. Tam and myself they
have the data they know what's what's
actually happening on the ground and so
we can see in the province of Quebec
that what's happening on the island of
Montreal and how they may be relaxing
their measures a you know maybe in a
slower fashion based on the epidemiology
of what's happening in one trellis
compared to the rest of the province of
Quebec that's that's a prime example
that even with any province that there
needs to be a careful look at obviously
taking account what's happening locally
to make the best possible decisions
based on what what they know in terms of
the epidemiology thank you thank you
upper next question Thank You Missy the
portion disco madness tell the developer
to move hi dr. Tim my question is for
you I think I have an idea of the answer
but I would like to hear you explain why
is your recommendation today on non
surgical masks why is it only a
recommendation and why are you not
making it mandatory canada-wide to wear
a mask when we go outside is it a
question of jurisdiction is it a
question of their just wouldn't be
enough masks to make it mandatory is it
a question of Rights can you explain why
it remains only a recommendation it's
like the National OVA remains a
recommendation and asks the meta causes
of health needs to look at their own
particular context in terms of whether
they actually have evidence of community
transmission and some areas actually
don't and have actually never had
community transmission it's very
different from say maybe you know
compare doctor news at comparing
Montreal and Toronto to Yukon or the PEI
might actually be very different so they
need that ability to make those
recommendations their public
transportation systems might be
different for example and so they they
need the ability to do that risk
assessment and recommend it from from
their
- from the federal perspective and
Transport Canada of course given that
the federal jurisdiction did make with
the wearing of non-medical masks
mandatory on those conveniences so that
is within the federal jurisdiction its
doctrine you maybe I just add certainly
understand that the interest in terms of
the use of a non-medical mask you know
by the general public but one of the
issues were also obviously with our
counterparts and provinces and
territories looking at closely is that
the unintended consequences where if you
people think that by wearing a mask in
public they don't need to follow all of
the other important public health
measures that we've been underlining uh
so many times in terms of guarding you
know that the distance of physical
distancing of 2 meters etc so that's one
of the things I think we still need to
underline that this is quote a
supplementary measure that people can
use to protect themselves when it's
difficult to maintain that physical
distancing of 2 meters but it certainly
does not replace all of the other good
measures such as hand-washing etc thanks
another follow-up - sorry there's an
echo as a follow-up dr. Tim so that as
you mentioned previously it was already
suggested to wear a non-medical mask
when we go outside now it's recommended
but in in places like Quebec for example
it has been recommended strongly
recommended for a week already and we
see that people are not necessarily
wearing it outside at the grocery store
or in other locations where they can't
social distance so what exactly can you
do as public health officials to ensure
that something actually changes on the
ground your language is changing but
people aren't wearing it more I can't
speak to the very local jurisdiction and
they will adjust their approach as
needed but I think from certain public
opinion research etc Canadians are
wearing more masks and they are more
that the social cultural shift is
beginning to occur
so part of what public health is doing
is you know the concept is one I think
of reciprocal protection so I think for
Canadians thinking of it as I'm
protecting you and you're protecting me
is a very key concept we have to gain
the trust of the Canadian public and get
their buy-in to do all of this mandating
is one measure which some jurisdictions
might take if they have to but for the
most part I do think that the shift is
occurring in the population as well
which I think is is great thank you
doctor will now turn to the room first
question yeah
Ryan Templeton with the National Post
the pan Canadian Public Health Care
Network which you're chair of wrote a
report in 2016 called a blueprint for a
federated system of Public Health
surveillance it recommended that
provinces and the feds work closer
together it said there were gaps and how
they share data said there were
differences in how they collect data I'm
wondering sort of what progress has been
made on implementing that reports
recommendations to a more aligned system
between the provinces and the federal
government yes so I think data is
extremely important obviously to any
outbreak and you know pandemic is into
this scale from a regular outbreak
perspective we have some very well run
mechanisms your foodborne outbreaks
being a very key concept of this is that
we react very fast information is shared
and but
but something of this scale and the
respiratory domain that's obviously some
gaps particularly reporting to the
national level that we do have to
address some of it is timeliness but
some of the fields cannot be completed
by the jurisdictions at the moment when
we look at the completion rates so we
are actively trying very hard to figure
out where what is needed is it more
support
at different levels is that can the
system be made more efficient because
efficiency in the system helps our
frontline public health workers as well
who are very busy doing certain things
that the sister there may be system
efficiencies of course the day that
comes from many different areas and it's
the complexity of the Canadian landscape
of data I think some data has to come
from hospitals they come from labs it
has to come from local public health
units and that so but I think it is
absolutely recognized and also at the
First Minister's level that this is an
absolutely another chance for us to
improve on what we're doing but you know
I think capitalizing on the sort of
crisis that we have we need to give it
an another good go for the next piece
thank you follow-up yeah I'm wondering
what were those what are sort of the
barriers in bringing this data together
is it jurisdictional is it the provinces
don't want to ease up on their control
over health care and also do you think
not having shared data has hindered our
ability to respond to this pandemic so
we it is a federated system and the
public health system is a local level up
system and we collaborate to get data so
that's always been the construct is one
of a collaborative approach and so the
most important thing of course is at the
local level they have the data that they
need to actually respond to the
identification of cases and the
follow-up of contacts which we all know
is very important that's the key
so then is the reporting then from the
local jurisdiction to the provincial
level that has to be sort of that is
under the jurisdiction of the provinces
and territories from the province to the
federal level is we at the federal level
don't do the day-to-day case management
that the data is needed and the data is
useful to the local drinks and they have
been action
they have been providing advise public
health advice based on the local level
information but it is important to get
the national picture and to be able to
provide that to policymakers as well so
I think we have the basic information in
but I think what people needed and it's
asking for now is more what we call this
aggregation more in-depth analysis we
have things that age or sex but there is
a need to have First Nations Inuit matey
data as well as race ethnicity base data
as well so those are the kind of things
that we need to work on because if
you're fine-tuning your policies to
support vulnerable populations that's
important we do know of course we have
data for example to provide measures or
policies or programs to those most at
risk which is the seniors and the people
with underlying medical conditions etc
so that those the kind of data is
available is driving the response right
now as you can see in the different
jurisdictions in long term care but I
think it is important to take that next
stage so that we have a more in-depth
analysis to further support particularly
vulnerable populations thank you next
question CTV hi doctors Molly Thomas CTV
national news dr. Tam I understand you
know more evidence of asymptomatic
symptoms has influenced the mask
recommendation but did we drop the ball
here I mean I think of smaller country
it's a Czech Republic Vietnam even
Venezuela have had mandatory masks in
place for quite some time
do you regret this decision and could we
have prevented the spread here if it was
a different decision I think the
decision was taken to essentially ask
people to stay at home and they to the
quarren the the quarantine parents the
isolation of cases in quarantine of
contact has been the mainstay of the
recommendation so we have effectively
stopped and the B and D saturated that
epidemic wave so
that actually has been effective so when
I say they tried and true public health
versus those the identification of cases
contacts isolation quarantine
hand-washing physical distancing has
worked but you need so this is an added
layer on top of that and I do think that
it is important as we begin to reopen
that people no longer staying at home
more people will be going outside public
transit may be more crowded as a result
this will help us reopen and add another
layer to that how do you go out safely
message I think but the message the
Canadians must remain all of those you
know previous measures with this as an
added layer of protection and so then we
will still have to collect some
information that kind of data to show
the efficacy of the non-medical mass on
top of everything else might actually be
quite difficult to discern because that
multiple things are happening but it
would be very interesting still to try
and look in the Canadian context what
this has produced as as people adopt
this measure more widely no regrets
we need to flexibly you know change our
measures as we get more information but
as I've just said B has always been if
you were infectious that was at the
beginning when we thought that the
majority had symptoms you do what opaque
phase covering on to prevent
transmission the other if you even at
home looking after sick person yes this
isn't sing but the mask so I think
adding on this layer as we know more was
the appropriate thing to do and I think
we need to focus on the here and there
the whole hindsight thing people can
review but maybe on all future
respiratory outbreaks this will be the
actual norm to do and so I think we need
to sort of look forwards to what might
be the approach in Canada
about testing um so you said on average
we're testing about 28,000 people a day
week and a half ago I talked to you I
think it was 26,000 on average so we're
like a slow crawl up to that goal of
60,000 what is the holdup here so 60,000
is the capacity that is already there
for public health labs so your question
is why are we only doing you know 28 or
maybe higher some days they it is higher
this is a bit of an average so this is
something that at the highest levels of
governments people are seized with a lot
of this in talking to the chief medical
for example in British Columbia they
just said that their level of infection
has really come down there's no one with
much in the way of a respiratory illness
they will of course widen everybody is
widening their community testing to
include even mild symptoms and sometimes
people are not actually showing up and
so it depends I think on the access the
uptake of the testing on the ground not
necessary because they don't have the
capacity but also because of what the
local Medical says feel to be in line
with where they are in the epidemic but
having said that we looking at
absolutely
how do we appropriately increase testing
for example you've seen in certain
provinces they're looking at the
vulnerable settings a long-term care
where they are looking at testing people
in that setting whether they're
symptomatic or not and the people who
work there so there's so there's also
systemic pilots or surveillance being
done in different jurisdictions and
we're going to share the information
across the country to see if people can
learn from each other as to what's the
appropriate area for increasing testing
so all that is at play but the key is
that you need to have a sensitive enough
system to detect any resurgence of cases
and then clamp down on the contact so
that is the fundamental principle
thank you next question on toast our dr.
Jim Hite endemic Charles with the star
I'm well duck leads to what I was going
to ask you about but so specifically
since you've talked so much today on so
many topics about the need to respect
jurisdictions I'm curious what exactly
are the elements that the federal level
has proposed as a national framework on
testing and contact tracing that the
prime minister said was tabled last week
two provinces so I think or province
territories know that the sum of the
three fundamental aspects so the
criteria and the indicators are sort of
laid down in in the recommendations or
the guidance of the special advisory
committee which is the family how
foundation for which testing contact
tracing and then isolation and
Quarantine is the fundamental public
health underpinnings or principle for
this next phase so everybody knows that
that is absolutely critical everybody
knows that we have to increase capacity
to detect any resurgence and build a
capacity towards any potential increase
if we're to see that in the fore we hope
that we can sort of clamp down on you
know any sparks and introductions show
the suppression of any sparks is really
key I think the federal government's key
role is I think the the Prime Minister
offered resources support to the
provinces as needed to ramp up their
capacity we are supporting of course
applies swabs reagents if there's a need
for any other further support as well
and you know committed to you know
looking at what else the province is
needs we provide guidance of course and
these updated as as appropriate so to
look at what population needs to be
tested over time as well so actually
Phil national framework on testing and
contract tracing proposed then it is it
is it overstating the case to say that
you've proposed a national framework on
how testing and contact tracing should
go forward you've just referred to
guidelines that and criteria that you
came up with weeks ago so because
there's something new been put on the
table or no so I think that speaks to
the a higher level commitment that is a
wider strategy I think that is not just
of course the technical guidance but
looking at supplies and other resources
and support that would be required but
fundamentally we've always had a
strategy for laboratory testing which is
founded on public health guidance and
that changes over time so at the
beginning it was targeted more at
travelers because of the that's where
the epidemiology is at at the peak of at
the epidemic it is focused and people
are asked to stay at home and if they
have mild symptoms and so at that stage
the testing approach the strategy is
focused on the sickest people and areas
of outbreaks like long term care and
health care workers as we begin to get
this first way from the control and into
this recovery reopening phase is about
widening then that testing for example
to people with mild symptoms who would
never sort of in the previous phase was
necessary tested now we're expanding the
testing to particularly symptomatic but
with mild symptoms as well as a very low
threshold for testing everybody in under
certain high-risk settings whether it be
long term care acute care correctional
services shelters indigenous populations
that are at higher risk of their severe
impacts and so this is fundamental to
the strategy and also then how do we
widen surveillance and having
surveillance systems which are built
upon respiratory illness surveillance
but maybe there are others
surveillance approaches that we can take
we call those pilots or surveillance
activities which can take into account
for example the testing of asymptomatic
people so that is the actual approach
which varies and will be adapted so I
think is an adapter an adaptive testing
strategy which is now moving into the
next phase at the same time as doing
that ramping up our capacity in every
single channel that we can so the other
aspect of the strategy is that right now
there are three modalities we're looking
at one the existing ramping up after
laboratory based PCR testing that is the
key to testing whether you have the
infection now widening that from the lab
base to point of care so that's part of
the strategy getting point of care test
getting supplies particularly to cover
the rural and more remote areas that is
still a work in progress we're getting
gene expert an expert Express task heavy
to test kits now you've seen the lelouch
you've seen nineveh and others having
these supplies so point-of-care
particularly to coverage those areas
very important thirdly you've heard the
immunity task force
serology will become the third component
of the testing strategy one the primary
key aspect of that as you've probably
already heard is to conduct those Cyril
surveys which we believe will be
conducted pretty fast to uncover how
much of the population what's the
prevalence and how much of the
population has been infected that is
important for policy decisions not just
now but as we get a vaccine for example
in the future to know what the
population immunity is and where we
might be going with vaccination
strategies those same prevalence studies
together with actual research on the
immunology of the response to of the
body the antibody response you're in
aspects of immune response will then
help the further use of serology for an
individual diagnostic basis right now
that is not ready for prime time so that
to me lays out the actual strategy and
the modalities or the testing approaches
but fortunately there's a lot of
research right now and there will be
other tests that could potentially be
available at which point those will be
also be scoped into the strategy itself
thank you doctor we'll go back to the
phone operator thank you missing the
question just Joe Michel Michigan laughs
number that you can a dollop on a little
can I didn't they be Monday they're not
just now saw Jean not even Aetna I
invested oh come on - you want a party
pony LaValle the truth lead the chef the
disaster for TPD to be prevented see
Jackie Onassis aftermath of oscillating
in a mandate Amina Java digital next
apologies chances doctor new we are
sister continuity no comedy no actually
dr. Tammy mile on continued no
discussion of a canoes AMA log Lhasa
astrology ocss volley way Odaiba del
upon Dionisio Canada no no no not
recommendation Stacy basis corner of a
solitary sake Lapua order the
transmission see see see
cozy Papa dear lady Paxson asymptomatic
may avec l experience or see a trivial
amount is co2 Canada on a preacher say
you see pacifically taxon asymptomatic
proof transmitted relievers or OC
madnikey says just unzip exactly McHale
property of pox on Tasha
apostasy on kolhapure contact ela
transmission CC power partly attacks on
matic may avec la vie de smet now on
discreet a on astrology dr. Tamara and
the OOD be the messenger additional
shifted today Provenza territoire
tomorrow with even consist for their
case a common concept permissive met now
a veca iveco see the shanshu avec le
jurisdiction is that mistress only
diplomacy target work he some pre-med
now i sooo clear the problem is really
salty public savvy do
okay Matt no tomorrow a vaguely repeated
tomorrow epithet pulastya Cesare
available toe of a sock did Lomenzo may
vector say potato
a note comedian note yes pathetically
Alicia can delay the transfer coming up
that Don is all familiar secede EST
difficile Giardia in this distillation
of physic to the Metra please say a
vector a vector c ii stance kishan
shaker with a Beckley table keke zombie
a curly misogynist chef diplomacy terry
12 at dr. Tenma on a mat not down
committee unless past the OKC prison
recommendation Sumiyoshi da second
circumstance apart at rubella PE on a de
jure constituted within a circumstance
kiss-kiss pass actual memoria say
complement different ever kiss kiss Paso
oh no her beckretary talk say such a
poo corner
Sanji potato and pokemon they made on
second sector and circumstance discuss
it prefer met now let's see
SQL in the thick of easily be broken
apart let's see me s character in Sydney
sports optimal security pass corners we
know the offense a man was our well
collision doctor please me no respect
relates consciousness is Nicola as
Josefina says the massage physically
disaster for the whole people specific
can be measured in elsewhere respective
a scale of my mouth
not one poker National Ballet of the
respective instance eviction
preocupacin me to Marcia
Takamiya news OTC and avec nous somme
melaka we see our Akumal net NOLA little
is a saw the mask nominee koa over
popular the popular songs general Posca
are we on purpose lastly Zota Monsieur
de Santi public key sundae jicama being
table AAS a secret sa isang Africa's
danke
the distance physical Dermot a slavish
who've only may forget the absolute ma
Delia de Bont concepted is not a public
the billabong reserve a sustained note
so c-come indeed to joy in a note Mia
super motel nurse a doctrinal peritoneum
Kassim Nestle thank you
the next question is from Althea arise
from the HuffPost Canada please go ahead
your line is now open
I thank you very much doctor tell my
question is about proper mask etiquette
a few weeks ago you were mentioning how
important this was but could you kindly
walk the public through how to take off
your mask properly when I go from one
store to another store can I reuse my
mask should I be putting on a new mask
should I be carrying a little baggy in
which to put my contaminated masks
what are what is proper mask etiquette
so I think I would also point people to
the website I'm trying to think Canada
dossier / coronavirus because it would
be easier I think for people to get the
different steps from from the
information as well and so yes so I
think one key some of the
recommendations pertain to materials in
fact there's actually quite interesting
studies now not now that there's more
interest in wearing non-medical masks
but
but the most basic materials are like
cotton but you have to have different
layers so that you when you hold it up
to the light I mean the light doesn't
shine through so there's different tips
as to what kind of materials use but I
think the other thing is also fit so
that you can't have you know gaping air
coming through the side of your mouth
for example so making sure that it fits
your your face and etc so hand washing
as we all know is the key to everything
and frequent hand washing so before you
put a mask when you're removing a mass
is actually very important as well and
try not to touch the external side of
your mass for instance but certainly
washing your hands and you can I think
carrying a set lock bag or something is
actually important because then you can
put your mask in it when you're not
wearing it now that is you're not
letting other people touch your mask I I
think that's very important and and that
you are using it yourself and using the
hand hygiene and of course the you know
having washable materials that you can
then wash in at home I think is
important but yeah don't use well you
definitely don't let other people touch
you masca your whole concept is
protecting other people if it's your own
secretions is your own secretions keep
it to yourself and wash your hands
really well I think thank you doctor
maybe I just add to that sort of a
practical sight so if you mentioned when
you're going from store to store the
most important thing you know you're
adjusting elastics this don't touch your
face right you know it's a it's a you
know you put your elastics here and put
them put your mask on and of course I
think I think many stores now or many
places in public have the obviously the
the hand sanitizers etc so if you are
then you adjust your mask and so on as
often as you can as dr. Tim says wash
your hands or take advantage of the hand
sanitizers as well but
the most important thing in terms of the
mask that we've seen is that it
sometimes gives people a false sense of
assurance and then they unknowingly or
whatever by fiddling with the mask they
end up touching their their face and as
we know that the most important parts to
try and protect and not touch because
that's how the virus enters are actually
your eyes your nose in your mouth that's
a really good point I think the key is
yes we have a lot of public health
always has a lot of you know key
messages in terms of because we're a bit
worried that with this added layer of
protection people forget other things
but I'm actually pretty confident in
Canadians I think people can learn and
adapt and this is one aspect that I
think we were all in as we go forward
together in the next days and months
Thank You LTF follow-up Thanks so we've
had a few questions from the public
about the wearing of masks and I'm
wondering I know you said obviously
circumstances are different across the
country but for people in urban centers
where there has been community spreads
would you like to see employers and if
they're employees in stores where masks
should joggers wear masks when they hit
crowded paths if you have folks over in
your back yard should these people be
wearing masks Thanks so I'm sure there's
a lot of different situations and
permutations and you know local medical
offices are no doubt answering very
similar questions as people restarts
certain businesses they in every
jurisdiction there's instructions in
terms of providing a plan for your
reopening which includes in many of the
situation what we call the hierarchy of
controls and in terms of protecting
staff but also customers and they don't
it's not just mask again is an added
layer of protection because you actually
have to look at physical barriers like
Plexiglas you have to look at schedules
you have to look at how you're going to
reduce and
other people perhaps whether it's in
your office setting or the store in
order to get that physical distancing so
that that physical distancing still
remains a fundamental aspect of this so
then you're looking at your specific
circumstances in terms of your workplace
what that workplace is who you're
serving and as to whether the
non-medical mass is appropriate but
obviously again the fundamental
principle being if you're in a crowded
space you can't maintain that 2 meter
distance I think the outdoors is
definitely less of a risk than indoors
so I think for people jogging if you're
on the outdoors and you you know just
sort of passing somewhere very quickly
that is a much lower risk than if you
were inside for sure
Thank You Daniel casting on telephone
operator thank you misrepresentation
Louis annual payroll dollar price we
bounced over Cisco honey ale about
Damascus tonight in the suggestion where
opera dont not below the comedy because
inconceivable around obligate waa
mixtape allocations the doctor new media
duties that sounded the mass Normandy
coast ACC Vermont kick show sister
coming module jobs after true self as
seen on per comercio CEO Padilla nausea
comedy interpolate us si sessions mother
not talk to Teresa dolly P I the West
City drama comedy deja and happy to
accommodate that nochmal pave Lily
resident EPE della Xia see an animal a
donut release to Java in mask
Sierra Co Sava oblique me
ECC in question de comedia that at
Kapalua less a doctor time
worker lopaka population and jam it now
ccc-come say please accept a on what the
please on please Lolita on kpop dance
posture l'ducation salsa Billy Zilla
population say koala lay the benefits
that the bacteria in master non-medical
only to Joseph Adama possibility sir
prodigy Cantrell is also from all potato
in Cinderella's Peppa gap tetra protge
lizard see a pathetic loser via the good
letter K shows it was a very very potato
lose that contaminate vaccarelli Vegas
the hawkers possible city sales listed
about basket and only prevented
territoire say say suleiman de l a
situational vehicle epidemiology
solitaire say it's a couple more
difference with into jelly point the
situation mauriello Santa will say
compliment if ever kiss kiss bath potato
Noah Donna Donna the Nunavut hidaka up
above water in committee politic at
reveille people's is the obligatory
Verma sparsity bunker ever kiss kiss
past sexual mama
Sula trained on Shack province it
territoire a sponsor that prey on
desperate pond any potato future avec le
so take Lucy on that the disaffection
desperate hua servitor comedy Lenoir
macaque shows are normal that the party
mask is here Sava dilemmas Arvika avakov
occur a vector2 comedy Rebecca a vacant
Abby to the nochmal maxi just answer me
example to conquer conquer risky ocean I
kill mama in the rear party on mascara
from Dallas area okay master PLO chief
justice the deficit of the word to this
example mayor serious potage but to job
debt
Danny cake is example that you till
Easter Joe Marcus Cory Booker my family
you see a myriad potentially concept
over his Oh tomorrow see my famiiy can
see see in sublimity Commedia util is a
fallacy on it alexia Via della me so if
the purpose if the Guardian in distance
no physic the Dometic a risk don't lie
in one example a transport come on sleep
I exactly Marquez key space actually mom
a evacuated to suffer death tomorrow Abu
couplet monkey IKEA give us dr. de la
camisa Asya honored on zanotab Ursus
it's a permission assisted tetraplegic
appear in distance the Dimetrodon c'est
bon idea Vasquez and Asia and
recommendation they did wrote this
authority has an eternal amore
allez-vous Quebec the party and mask in
not example since a member of a weekly
magazine pathetic rich Purnell example
see on a Don's in comedy in gras
magazine became beaucoup de Spassky a
truly Missouri Lily Lily Lily on tell
Ramona garden bond estado de mettre
pathetical spiciness the same
institution pathetic shows are
considered a compadre Petra CLE Dijon
casandra's MPT dependable Queen de la
vie
so say to Sheila membership cro NEPA
cessation if a perceptible rahman
distance that the de mettre please says
they denote the majestic LaMotta this
especially those example saw someone who
very next question cbc can I just add
that I again patients and and compassion
is needed in even looking at mask use I
just want to sort of remind people that
for for people with disabilities we need
to make sure that we have some
understanding as to their needs
including the wearing of non-medical
masks and particularly for mass and the
hearing impaired they
a communication partner for example
there needs to be consideration for
maybe having a clear face shield or
other means so that those who who are
hearing-impaired can continue to be sort
of considered in all of this so why I
think it's important for Canadians to so
the think of this measure as being you
protecting others and others protecting
you is to generate that concept of you
know solidarity really and so I think
please be very aware of those with
different types of cognitive
intellectual disabilities those who are
hearing impaired and others so just be
patient
and don't assume that someone who isn't
wearing a mask or is wearing something
different doesn't have an actual reason
for it thank you
CBC Julie Van Deusen CBC dr. Tam I'm
wondering if you could blame Canadians
for being confused it wasn't so long ago
that you said don't bother wearing a
mask because it might protect others but
it wouldn't do much for you now you're
saying if you wear one you protect me if
I wear one I protect you can you explain
the evolution so it's always been sort
of protecting others a non-medical mass
medical mass aside that's to prevent
with eyes covering on all PPE is to
prevent are you getting infected by
others particular health care workers
wearing non-medical mass has always been
a protecting others from if you're
infected so it's always you protecting
others and so at the beginning it was
about people who have symptoms who
should wear masks if you say in the home
setting on an airplane if you found
someone who is sick or going you know
you have to go to the clinic or
something then the sick person should
wear the mask now here you're
considering if you think about it if
you're in the community where there is
actual being transmission of the virus
just consider everybody as potentially
being that sick patient because you
can't actually tell okay so that's the
this change is asymptomatic people could
potentially be infected or potentially
transmitted again you're using that
covering to protect others so that
concept is the same all the way through
and but at this particular time when
people have used the tried and true
measure of staying at home and physical
distancing beginning to go outside and
beginning to get to those more crowded
places where you can't control that 2
meter distance wearing the non-medical
mass of facial covering again protects
others from you if you happen to be
infected and there's a reciprocal thing
so if everybody is wearing a mask you're
protecting others and by the other way
around they're protecting you as well so
could you just explain what exactly is
new today
about what you're talking about because
in the past week or so two weeks you've
said wear a cloth mask if you go to a
crowded place like a grocery store if
you can't keep physical distancing now
you're saying the same thing today
except you're recommending it what is
different especially if it's voluntary
even in hot zones like what is the news
today could you please explain that very
clearly well there's no actual real news
and if the key is that we're about to
post the actual wording which I've been
actually communicating for some time and
it is based on a consensus with the
other chief mark houses of health so
that it's pretty provide further
clarification I think across the country
but there is flexibility as I said for
the local medical sustaining on their
situation and risk assessment to
recommend that to their local population
and you have to listen to your local
public health big differences you're
putting it on your website is that the
news what you've been saying for like
the last 10 days for that yes okay thank
you thank you Julian last question Mike
hello dr. Tim this this your you're
testing 28,000 a day
the lab capacity is 60,000 so basically
we're not testing 60,000 today a day
because we're gonna get false positives
we're going to get false negatives it's
not it's not helpful but say there was
30 clusters that just exploded out out
there do we have the capacity today to
do 60,000 lab tests a day if we need to
yes and it's not us or the federal
government this is the public health
system in Canada so that is their
capacity so they can ramp up if there's
a cluster that needed to be tested
of course this capacity is distributed
across the country if there is a
particular area of country where let's
say you in northern Saskatchewan you get
an outbreak the key is that we will
support whichever jurisdiction was
searched if they need that too so that's
that's really important because the
capacity is easier to reach if you were
closer to the biggest centers we are
going to be sort of supporting the more
remote areas but even the point-of-care
test is a machine you have to be trained
to how to use that but they can be
deployed they can be reinforced so that
what you brought up is a really
important point if you spot the case in
the contest if there's a cluster you got
to move in really fast
and the laboratory capacity is designed
to be able to do that ok and we have all
the supplies and stuff ready to go in
case this is this hat this has happens
tomorrow or a month from now yes so I
thought this moment I know that there's
enough supplies but as you know every
day all those situations could change
and we work every single day to make
sure that we have what we need
so that is the capacity that we have but
that doesn't mean that tomorrow I may
not tell you that there's a potential
issue or something but the good news is
that there's more more capacity and
there's more more domestic capacity
thank you system offender confirms the
pathology
you